Today's דף *daf* is ל"ו *Lamed Vav*, 36. We pick up at
the bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב' *Lamed He Amud Bet* right before
the lines get wide, the two dots. And we are dealing with
what type, what constitutes שבועת העדות shevuat ha-edut *Shvuat Ha'edut*? What is
the type of language for שבועה shevuah, *shvua*? What constitutes a שבועה
shevuah, *shvua*? The משנה Mishna *Mishnah* mentioned different languages, משביע mashbia אני
עליכם *Mashpiah Ani Aleichem*, מצוה אני עליכם *Metzaveh Ani Aleichem*. So that
even sounded like you didn't need a language of שבועה shevuah, *shvua*
at all, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* modified that by saying no,
no, no, it means מצוה אני עליכם בשבועה *Metzaveh Ani Aleichem Bishvua*.
You do mention some keyword of שבועה shevuah *shvua* when we dealt
earlier with שבועת ביטוי *Shvuat Bitui*. We also learned that there were
other words that were synonymous with שבועה shevuah, *shvua*, but you need
some שבועה shevuah *shvua* language. Okay, and then we also, the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* continued and then it continued that you also need a,
what do you call it, you need to use God's name, you
know, and it said you don't need God's name exactly י-ה-ו-ה *Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei*.
You could have א-ד-נ-י *Aleph-Daled-Nun-Yod*, צבאות *Tzevaot*, other questions, which starts a
whole discussion of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about what constitutes God's name
for the purposes of the prohibition against erasing it and so on.
But you do need God's name. And that's interesting because when we
learned earlier discussions of שבועת ביטוי *Shvuat Bitui*, I raised the question
from the very beginning of the מסכת Masechet *Masechet*, how much is
for something to constitute a שבועה shevuah. *shvua*, does God's name have
to be part of it, at least implicitly, maybe explicitly? And here's
finally, finally where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is addressing that issue. So
let's take a look as we pick up with two lines before
the lines get wide on ל"ה עמוד ב' *Lamed He Amud Bet*.
ובכל הכינויים הרי אלו חייבים *Uvechol hakinnuyim harei elu chayavim*. רמיניהי *Reminihi*,
I'll ask you on this, that a כינוי kinuy *kinnui*, a, you
know, euphemism or whatever, a, not God's explicit name, one of the
other names of God suffices. So it says, I'll ask you on
this, ויתן ה' אותך לאלה ולשבועה *Veyiten Hashem Otach Le'alah Velishvua*. So
this is by the סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*. God should make you for
a curse and an oath. מה תלמוד לומר Ma talmud lomar? *Ma
talmud lomar*? והלא כבר נאמר והשביע הכהן את האשה בשבועת האלה v'hishbia
hakohein es ha'isha b'shevuas ha'ala. *Vehalo kevar ne'emar vehishbia hakohen et ha'ishah
bishvuat ha'alah*. Or it said that he makes her, he adjures her
with the oath of the cursing. So why does it have to
again refer to repeat the words אלה alah *alah* and שבועה shevuah
*shvua* and even use God's name? לפי שנאמר *Lefi shene'emar*, the reason
it repeats it by a סוטה Sotah. *Sotah* is to teach you
something about שבועת העדות shevuat ha-edut *Shvuat Ha'edut*. Because by שבועת העדות
shevuat ha-edut *Shvuat Ha'edut* it says ושמעה קול אלה v'shama kol alah
*Veshama Kol Alah*. And he will hear the sound of a curse.
Notice by the way, it never even says oath by שבועת העדות
shevuat ha-edut *Shvuat Ha'edut*. So נאמר כאן אלה alah, ונאמר להלן אלה
alah *Ne'emar kan alah vene'emar lehalan alah*. So it says it here
and it says it over there. מה להלן שבועה shevuah *Ma lehalan
shvua*, the same way by סוטה Sotah *Sotah* the word אלה alah,
*alah* is a שבועת האלה shvuas ha'alah, *shvuat ha'alah*, it's a type
of an oath. אף כאן שבועה shevuah *Af kan shvua*, here too.
So number one, the very idea that by a שבועת העדות shevuat
ha-edut *Shvuat Ha'edut*, you know, we don't even know, the Torah never
even says it's a שבועה shevuah *shvua*, it says it's a curse.
I curse you if you don't come and testify for me. No,
so how do we know it's a שבועה shevuah. *shvua*? Oh, we
only learn it because the word אלה alah *alah* is used with
שבועה shevuah *shvua* by סוטה Sotah? *Sotah*. Okay, that's number one. Okay,
now מה להלן בשם ba-shem, אף כאן בשם ba-shem. *Ma lehalan beshem
af kan beshem*. Here's another thing we learn from סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*.
מה להלן בשם ba-shem, אף כאן בשם *Ma lehalan beshem af kan
beshem*. There it says ויתן ה' אותך *Veyiten Hashem otach*. Okay, God.
So it's a שבועה shevuah. *shvua* with God's name. So the two
major components of what constitutes a שבועת העדות shevuat ha-edut. *Shvuat Ha'edut*,
neither of which appear by שבועת העדות Shvuas HaEidus *Shvuat Ha'edut*. They're
both learned because the אלה alah *alah* makes us, you know, refers
us to the פרשת סוטה Sotah *Parshat Sotah*. Okay, so
why is that a problem with our משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*? That's all
very nice. That tells us the source of the basic components of
שבועת העדות shvuas ha'eidus *Shvuat Ha'edut*. How does it go against our
משנה Mishna *Mishnah*? Because our משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says that you're חייב
chayav בכל הכינויים *chayav bechol hakinnuyim* with even a substitute of God's
name. רחום חנון *Rachum, Chanun*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* modified that to
say it's not enough to say may רחום *Rachum* curse you, you
have to say may the one who is called רחום *Rachum* curse
you. Okay, it's actually interesting whether a name like רחום *Rachum* is
a descriptor, not a proper name. A כינוי kinuy *kinnui* would be
אל El, *El*, שדי Shakai, *Shaddai* and so on. Okay, so anyway
but it includes either God's name or a descriptor referring to God,
but not בשם *beshem*. Normally means the actual שם הויה shem Havayah.
*Shem Havayah*, י-ה-ו-ה *Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei*. So what is it? Do you need שם
הויה shem Havayah, *Shem Havayah*? Do you not need שם הויה shem
Havayah, *Shem Havayah*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר אביי לא
קשיא *Amar Abaye lo kashya*, it's not difficult. הא רבי חנינא בר
אידי Rabbi Chanina bar Idi. הא רבנן Rabanan. *Ha Rabbi Chanina bar
Idi ha Rabbanan*. It's a debate of תנאים tenaim *Tannaim* whether by
שבועת העדות shvuas ha'eidus? *Shvuat Ha'edut* you need שם הויה shem Havayah.
*Shem Havayah*. דתניא *Detanya*, we learn in a ברייתא braita *Baraita*, רבי
חנינא בר אידי Rabbi Chanina bar Idi אומר *Rabbi Chanina bar Idi
omer*, הואיל ואמרה תורה Torah, השבע ואל תשבע *Ho'il ve'amrah Torah hashba
ve'al tishavea*. Since the
Torah says sometimes you must take an oath and sometimes it says
you may not take an oath. When does it say you must
take an oath? So when it says you must take an oath,
it's שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם *Shvuat Hashem tihiyeh bein shneihem*, which
we're going to learn, certain types of oaths when there's a case
of litigant, you know, about a שומר *shomer* or about the guy
who admits partially. So sometimes it says he must take an oath
and it says don't take an oath, לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר Lo
tishave'u bishmi lashaker. *Lo tishavu bishmi lashaker*. Okay, so, so קלל ואל
תקלל
*Kallel ve'al tikhallel*. Sometimes it says curse. When are we supposed to
curse in the Torah? So when are we supposed to?
ויתן ה' אותך לאלה ולשבועה *Veyiten Hashem otach le'alah velishvua*.
Right, exactly. So by a סוטה Sotah *Sotah*, it, you know, you
give the curse to the סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*. And it says לא
תקלל, לא תקלל חרש, Lo tekalel cheresh, אלהים לא תקלל, Elohim lo
tekalel, right, so there are these prohibitions against cursing. Notice again, there's
the אלה alah and the שבועה, shevuah, the curse and the oath.
So מה השבע בשם אף לא תשבע בשם. mah hishava ba-shem af
lo tishava ba-shem. The same way taking the oath is with God's
name, okay, then not taking it is with God's name. Now what
do you know taking the oath is with God's name? So presumably
it's from this case of סוטה, Sotah, right, יתן ה׳ אותך. yiten
Hashem otach. But I have to tell you that that's actually quite
ironic because it's actually more explicit in the opposite way. לא תשבעו
בשמי לשקר. lo tishavu bishmi lashaker לא תשא את שם ה׳ אלהיך
לשוא. Lo tisa et shem Hashem Elokecha lashav.
So actually it's more explicit that the prohibition against a שבועה, shevuah,
a false שבועה, shevuah. a שבועה Shvua in vain is with שם
ה׳. shem Hashem. Okay, anyway, and therefore the same about, you know,
we could say about a normal שבועה, Shvua about, you know, about
a שבועת העדות shvuas ha'eidus or the שבועה Shvua. by סוטה. Sotah
So anyway, that's interesting that it seems to be going in the
opposite direction. But okay, from סוטה Sotah, we learn that שם ה׳.
shem Hashem.
What midrash did she take, the סוטה?
Sotah Well, she just, she just accepts it. Okay, so that's being
מושבע מפי אחרים, mushba mi-pi acherim, okay. But it said an אלה,
alah.
not a שבועה. Shvua Which? I still don't understand.
We'll get to, we'll get to, we'll get to the אלה alah
שבועה Shvua, distinction in a minute. Okay. So מה קלל בשם אף
לא תקלל בשם. mah kilel ba-shem af lo tekalel ba-shem. And the
same way it says by סוטה, Sotah, that's more clear evidence that
you need שם ה׳, shem Hashem, right, it says because שבועת האלה
יתן ה׳ אותך, shevuat ha-alah yiten Hashem otach, that's invoking God in
a קללה kelalah context. So when you're not allowed to curse, don't
curse God, don't curse the חרש, cheresh, don't curse a parent, okay,
that's also with the use of God's name. All right, so again,
it's interesting because I would have thought that the שבועה Shvua is
more explicit where the don't do the שבועה Shvua is with God's
name. But somehow, anyway, I learn out that all of these involve
God's name. Okay, so that is, but notice that that is רבי
חנינא בר אידי. Rabbi Chanina bar Idi, So what we're going to
say is רבי חנינא בר אידי Rabbi Chanina Bar Idai is the
author of the previous ברייתא braita: that also learned out from סוטה
Sotah that it's בשם, that it's with God's name, the שבועת העדות
shvuas ha'eidus. learned from סוטה Sotah it's בשם. And this is רבי
חנינא בר אידי'ס Rabbi Chanina bar Idi's general approach that it's all
בשם, שם הויה. shem Havayah But the author of our משנה Mishna
that says you can do a כינוי kinuy, is the רבנן. Rabanan
Okay, so some anonymous רבנן Rabanan, that disagree with him. So now
the question is going to be as the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to
say, so, you know, how do you know, well let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says רבנן, Rabanan, let's understand,
but בית דין Beit Din would still do the שם ה׳ shem
Hashem presumably, right? It's just only if you also did it with
כינוי Kinuy, then they might be חייב chayav also as well.
By some it would be... well, the שבועת העדות shvuat haedut is
imposed by the litigant, not by the בית דין. Beit Din. But
you're talking about let's say a שבועת הפקדון shevuat ha-pikadon or one
of those other things. Whatever. Right. Yeah, yeah, okay. So let's take
a look. רבנן, now the Rabbis, אי גמירי גזירה שוה, i g'miri
gzera shava, let's understand the Rabbis' position. Where did they get their
position from? If they have the link, the גזירה שוה, gzera shava,
the link to סוטה, Sotah מבעי שם המיוחד, mibai shem ha-meyuchad,
then they should come up to the same position that of רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina בר אידי, it should require God's, you know, יוד-ה-ו-ה-ing.
Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei אי לא גמירי גזירה שוה, i lo g'miri gzera shava, and
if they don't hold of the גזירה שוה gzera shava and they
don't learn anything from
סוטה, Sotah so אלה דשבועה היא מנלהו. alah d'shvuah hi minalhu. How
do you know by שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut we're talking about a
שבועה Shvua altogether? The verse says a curse. So the link to
סוטה Sotah? lets us learn that curse means an oath. But if,
but that would also require us to assume that you need שם
ה׳. shem Hashem. So make up your mind. Either you need שם
ה׳ shem Hashem or we're not talking about a שבועה. Shvua, How
do you know we're talking about a שבועה Shvua without שם ה׳?
shem Hashem? So the
גמרא Gemara, says נפקא להו מדתניא, nafka lehu m'de-tanya, no, they learn
it from somewhere else, because we taught in a ברייתא: braita. אלה,
alah meaning, and yes we are going to learn it from סוטה,
Sotah, but we're not going to learn it by a גזירה שוה.
gzera shava. A גזירה שוה gzera shava would have required us to
learn everything and שם ה׳. shem Hashem. We're just going to learn
from סוטה Sotah like we're Bible scholars and we want to understand
what does this word אלה alah mean. Let's see how it's used
elsewhere. Oh, by סוטה, Sotah. it's used in the context of an
oath. So אלה alah means something that takes place with an oath.
Okay, it's not גזירה שוה, gzera shava, it's just a meaning of
the word. And that's how we know that the אלה alah by
שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut. is a שבועה. Shvua. One minute.
מדתניא, m'de-tanya, אלה. alah It says ושמעה קול אלה v'shama kol alah,
by שבועת העדות. shvuat ha'edut. אין אלה אלא לשון שבועה. ein alah
ela lashon shevuah. What does אלה alah. mean? Oh, let's get out
our
BDB, okay, BDB is a classic reference work for Bible scholars, okay,
let's get out our concordance, let's try to figure out what the
word אלה alah means. It's not גזירה שוה, gzera shava, it's just
figure it out by context. אלה alah means שבועה, Shvua וכן הוא
אומר והשביע הכהן את האשה בשבועת האלה. v'chen hu omer v'hishbiya ha-kohen
et ha-ishah b'shvuat ha-alah. התם שבועת האלה כתיב. hatam shevuat ha-alah ketiv.
Okay, so that's how we know it. So yes, we learn it
from סוטה Sota. but not with a גזירה שוה. gzera shava. And
therefore we don't also learn the idea of שם ה׳. shem Hashem.
Now the question you should be asking is, then how do you
know that you need any reference to God? How you know you
need a כינוי, Kinuy? right? The Rabbis don't say it's enough to
just say שבועה, Shvua, that you need some
reference במי ששמו רחום, b'mi she-shmo rachum, במי ששמו חנון, b'mi she-shmo
chanun, א-ל, ש-די, etc., right? Where do you get this middle position
that, that's what bothers me. Very nice, the word אלה alah means
שבועה. Shvua, But how do you know that it needs some reference
to God but it doesn't need שם המיוחד? Shem HaMeyuchad? Okay, so
take so that's not clear. Right? So
let me just see one minute, I think who says something תוספות?
Tosafos?
No.
Okay, so no, so nobody actually directly addresses this issue about how
do you need any reference to God's name. I think that the
implication is
that—and this gets back to what we were saying since the beginning
of the פרק, Perek, since the beginning of the
מסכת—that Masechet something, any שבועה Shvua, by definition, the meaning of the
שבועה Shvua is, is that you are calling upon God to witness
something. God's name is always understood to be somehow like implicit or
explicit in a שבועה. Shvua. That's what a שבועה Shvua. is about.
Okay, so therefore even if you don't learn from סוטה Sota that
there's an explicit verse that requires שם השם, Shem HaShem, because if
you were to learn it from סוטה Sotah, you would need שם
המיוחד. Shem HaMeyuchad. Once we understand that what we're talking about here
is a שבועה, shvua. somehow we also implicitly understand that there needs
to be some reference to God. So therefore, that's you know the
משנה Mishna says it doesn't have to be שם המיוחד, Shem HaMeyuchad,
it could be a כינוי, kinuy. it could be במי ששמו רחום
וחנון bi-mi she-shmo rachum ve-chanun etc., but there does need to be
some reference to God. Okay, so but it's very—it's fascinating that the
גמרא—and Gemara this gets back to the theme I've been mentioning from
the beginning of the מסכת—that once the גמרא Gemara says okay I
know שבועה shvua? and I don't know שם הוי', Shem HaVaya, it's
never stopped to say but how do you know you need a
כינוי? kinuy. How do you know you need some reference to God?
The fact that it doesn't ask that shows in my mind that
it understands that every שבועה shvua implicitly right is about referencing God.
And I want to remind you about the debate between רמב"ם Rambam
and ראב"ד Ra'avad that we said—that we mentioned earlier. רמב"ם Rambam says
this explicitly, that no קרבן, Korban,
negative prohibition, no consequences of a שבועה shvua? apply without God's name—doesn't
have to be שם הוי'—but Shem HaVaya without some reference to God
being made.
Like I swear I won't eat tomorrow.
Right, now ראב"ד—right Ra'avad now ראב"ד Ra'avad disagrees. ראב"ד Ra'avad says even
without referencing God it can function like a נדר, Neder, it can
create a sense of an obligation to do something, the same way
a נדר Neder doesn't have to reference God, it creates a status.
So what would you transgress? You wouldn't transgress לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר
lo tishavu bishmi lashaker or לא תשא את שם השם אלהיך לשוא—that
lo tisa shem Hashem Elokecha lashav is about שם השם—but Shem HaShem
you would transgress like לא יחל דברו, lo yachel dvaro, right, that
it creates an obligation, an abstract obligation that you would then violate.
Okay, but he does concede that when you put לא יחל דברו
lo yachel dvaro aside, okay,
then yes you know it is about referencing God's name and certainly
something like שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut? and שבועת הפקדון Shvuas HaPikadon does
require God's name. To transgress the prohibition of לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר
you need שם השם. Shem HaShem. Alright, so that's where we are
right now.
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina בר אידי says because of the reference to
סוטה Sotah. you need שם השם. Shem HaShem. The Rabbis say you
just need שבועה, shvua and somehow even though they don't have any
explicit requirement of שם השם, Shem HaShem, or any explicit basis for
requiring God's name, because it's a שבועה shvua, that implicitly requires some
reference to God's name. Okay, yes.
So when they go to בית דין Beis Din and they—you know—what
they do—they both go to בית דין. Beis Din. Yeah. Do the
בית דין—does Beis Din everyone in בית דין Beis Din swear to
tell the truth? No. No, we've discussed this before.
Witnesses don't have to take a שבועה. shvua, The only people that
take a שבועה shvua. is when you have a חיוב שבועה, Chiyuv
Shvua, you know, in the Torah or a דרבנן DeRabanan חיוב שבועה.
Chiyuv Shvua. Okay. Okay, like שבועת הפקדון? Shvuas HaPikadon? Yeah. So why
don't we just learn from that? Well, because פקדון Pikadon we're going
to have to learn from פקדון Pikadon too. ובשמו תשבע, u-vishmo tishaveia,
right? Doesn't that mean—yeah, so we did learn from that. That was
מה שבועה בשם. mah Shvua ba-shem. So why be going to סוטה?
Sotah Why can't we just say, you know, talk about פקדון Pikadon
and say just like שבועת פקדון... Shvuas Pikadon... I know, that's what
רבי חנינא—that's what רבי חנינא says, he does go from there.
Okay,
first we have to get the word that אלה Alah, means שבועה,
shvua but
why—why doesn't everyone say that?
Because okay, because that would require שם המיוחד Shem HaMeyuchad and the
Rabbis don't think you need שם המיוחד. Shem HaMeyuchad. Why not? I
don't know, you can't—you can't force a גזירה שוה, Gezeirah Shavah, you
either have it or you don't. Okay, so אין אלה alah אלא
בשבועה—וכן הוא אומר... Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says התם—okay, hasam
so now we've learned for the Rabbis they don't make the link
to סוטה, Sotah they don't make the link to שבועת הפקדון, Shvuas
HaPikadon, they require שבועה, shvua. yes, but not שם הוי', Shem HaVaya,
not the explicit שם הוי'. Shem HaVaya. But now the גמרא Gemara,
says one minute, by סוטה Sotah; you can't learn that the word
אלה alah. means שבועה, shvua, that's not what it says by סוטה.
Sotah התם, hasam, says the גמרא, Gemara שבועת האלה כתיב, shvuas ha-alah
ksiv,
it says the שבועה shvua, of the אלה. alah. Okay, so the
word—that means like they're combined. It doesn't mean that the word אלה
alah, means a שבועה. shvua. It means I am משביע mashbia you
that if you are lying, God should come and bring you know
a plague on your house. Okay, so that doesn't mean the word
אלה alah. means שבועה. shvua; It means it's a curse that occurs
in the context of a שבועה. shvua How do you learn by
שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut? that the word אלה alah just means a
שבועה? shvua Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: הכא קאמר, hacha ka'amar,
here's what we mean. אלה, alah. אין אלה אלא בשבועה. ein alah
ela bishvua Fine, you're right. We don't go straight there. First thing
אלה alah means is a curse that comes in the context of
a שבועה shvua on someone. וכן הוא אומר והשביע הכהן את האשה
בשבועת האלה. v'chein hu omer v'hishbia hakohen es ha'isha bishvuas ha'alah. ומנין
לעשות—now uminayin la'asos the גמרא Gemara. says: But how do you know
to make—and we'll read I guess what's in parentheses—אלה שאינה עם שבועה
כאלה שישנה עם שבועה? alah she'eini im shvua k'alah she'yeshni im shvua?
How do you know that if you—you can separate the two? That
if you just say, "You should be cursed if you know testimony
and you're not coming to testify," without a שבועה? shvua Or שבועה
שאינה עם אלה כשבועה שישנה עם אלה? shvua she'eini im alah k'shvua
she'yeshni im alah? How do you know that a שבועה shvua? alone
is enough
to—for the purpose of שבועת העדות? Shvuas Ha'eidus. How do you know
that you don't require the two combined? תלמוד לומר ושמעה קול אלה.
talmud lomar v'shama kol alah. Okay, the sound of an אלה. alah
ושמעה אלה, v'shama alah, it could have just said you heard the
curse. What's ושמעה קול? v'shama kol? Okay, so we separate it. ושמעה
אלה ושמעה קול. v'shama alah v'shama kol. So it can be either
a sound, which is a שבועה, shevuah or an אלה. alah, It
could be either the curse by itself without a שבועה, shevuah. or
something that is called the voice, and here that extra word voice
we're going to say references a שבועה. shevuah So the fact that
it doesn't say שבועת האלה, shvuas ha'alah, which is the wrapping together
of the two, it says קול kol and אלה, alah we are
going to read that to tell me either a שבועה shevuah. or
an אלה. ala. So for the rabbis, it's not a גזירה שוה
gzeira shava to סוטה. Sotah The word קול kol and אלה ala
allow us to separate. And by the way, I don't know if
you noticed this and if this was mentioned yesterday when you did
the משנה, Mishna but the
משנה—this Mishna. whole thing about שבועת העדות—it Shuas Ha'eidus doesn't have to
be a שבועה. shevuah It could just be—all along we've been talking
about שבועה, shevuah שבועה, shevuah שבועה. shevuah. But if I actually come
and say, "God should curse you and bring a plague on your
house if you know עדות eidus to me and you're not coming
and testifying," and you say, "I don't know any עדות," eidus, and
then you're lying, then you bring the קרבן. korban. Okay, it doesn't
even require a שבועה; shevuah, it's enough to use a curse. How
do I know? If you look back in the משנה, Mishnah, the
משנה Mishnah, has the case. The משנה Mishnah, says: יככה ה' אלהים
וכן יככה אלהים זו היא האלה הכתובה בתורה. yakecha Hashem Elokeim v'chein
yakecha Elokeim zu hi ha'alah haksiva batorah. Do you remember that from
yesterday? "May God curse you," that's the אלה. ala So for the
rabbis, okay, right,
when it
says ושמעה קול אלה, shama kol alah, okay, קול kol means just
שבועה shvua, and אלה ala means just a קללה. klala. And either
one enough, or either one enough is sufficient for שבועת העדות. Shuas
Ha'eidus Okay, so yes, are they often wrapped
together? שבועת האלה, shevuas ha'ala. "I am משביע you that if you're
lying, God should curse you." But we are learning out that they
are separate things and either one is enough. And you don't need
שם ה'. shem Hashem. Somehow שבועה shvua implicitly is God's name the
same way קללה klala is implicitly God's name. You know, the example
the גמרא—the Gemara. משנה Mishnah gives: יככה ה'. yakecha Hashem. Right, so
that also—how do you know you need God's name? So somehow, if
you don't have a learning of שם המיוחד, shem hamuychad, you don't
need שם shem, הוי"ה, but even without שם הוי"ה, these two ideas
are meaningless without invoking God. So you have to—what? You could use
a כינוי. kinuy That's my point. So according to רבי חנינא בן
Rabi Chanina ben whatever, I think it's רבי אידי, Rabi Idi, right?
רבי
אידי. Rabi Idi. So you need—we learn out from סוטה Sotah that
it needs the שם המיוחד. shem hamuychad. But even without him, all—a
שבועה shvua or קללה klala minimally require some reference to God or
else it's not a meaningful point, right? "May God curse you," "may
God, you know, by God's name I, you know, I adjure you
to whatever, come and swear." Okay, so that's why we know that
you need a כינוי.
So I'm curious about the ו' vav or the "or", ושמעה קול
או אלה.
v'shama kol o alah. Yeah, I know, it's a big—well, that's an
earlier discussion of the גמרא, Gemara the ו' vav means "or" or
does it mean "and". But yes, there's no ו' vav there though.
ושמעה קול אלה, vashama kol ala
that's true.
Yeah, it's a good point. I don't know, I don't know. This
is why the גמרא Gemara again, you could have interpreted it to
mean both. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבי אבהו: Amar
Rabi Abahu: מנין minayin now...
anyway
let's look at this little תוספות: Tosfos: יככה וכן יכככם זו היא
אלה שנאמרה בתורה. yakecha v'chein yakechem zu hi alah shene'emra batorah. You
see that little תוספות? Tosfos? And he's referencing the משנה. Mishnah, He
says: תמה, Teima, דלעיל גמרינן אלא שבועה שאינה עם אלה כשישנה עם
אלה. de'leil gamrinan ala shvua she'eini im alah k'shishni im alah.
We only learn שבועה shvua by itself. אבל אלה שאינה עם שבועה
כשישנה עם שבועה מנלן? Aval alah she'eini im shvua k'shishni im shvua
minalan? How do we know אלה ala by itself, which shows that
he had a different גרסא, girsa, that's why they took it out
in the parentheses of our גמרא. Gemara Okay, but that's exactly somehow
what we're doing is we're saying קול kol and אלה, ala. we're
disentangling the two and saying one by itself is enough. Okay, so
now let's continue in the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי
אבהו: Amar Rabi Abahu: מנין לאלה שהיא שבועה? minayin l'alah she'hi shvua?
Okay,
now here's another learning. How do I know the word אלה ala
means שבועה? shvua שנאמר ויבא אתו באלה. shene'emar vayavei oso b'alah. Okay,
he brought him into the curse. וכתיב: uksiv: וגם במלך נבוכדנצר מרד
אשר. v'gam b'melech Nevuchadnetzar marad asher. who adjured him in God's name.
Okay, so you see that it uses the word שבועה shvua, in
one verse referring to what in another verse it referred to as
an אלה. ala So that's a very nice straight derivation, right? One
verse it refers to, he said he cursed him, and in another
verse it says that he he imposed an oath on him. So
you see sometimes the word אלה ala refers to an oath. That
was very nice. Okay, תנא, tana, we taught in a ברייתא. braita
ארור, arur, the word ארור, arur, if you say ארור arur this
person blah blah blah, בו נידוי bo niduy in some contexts it
means a נידוי, niduy, putting somebody in excommunication, בו קללה bo klala
in some cases it means a קללה, klala, which is what it
would simply mean, and בו שבועה bo shevuah and sometimes it means
an oath. And we're seeing that the word אלה ala also sometimes
means the word שבועה. shvua So similar the way אלה alah, can
mean the word oath, ארור arur can mean the word oath. בו
נידוי דכתיב, bo niduy d'ksiv, אורו מרוז, oru meroz, that is by
שירת דבורה. shiras Devorah. Cursed be
Meroz.
אמר מלאך ה', amar malach Hashem, אורו אורו יושביה. oru oru yoshveha.
So Meroz apparently was some important person who'd refused to go and
join with דבורה Devorah and ברק. Barak.
It's רש"י Rashi on
probably is a city because it says יושביה. yoshveha. רש"י Rashi on
תנ"ך Tanach says that it means a person, whatever it is, anyway
some place or some person who did not join in in the
battle. Okay, ואמר עולא, v'amar Ulla, בארבע מאה שיפורי שמתיה ברק למרוז.
b'arba me'ah shipurei shamteih Barak l'Meroz. So he didn't just say cursed,
the curse there means he put him in חרם cherem or he
put the city in חרם. cherem. Okay, so that's how we know,
I mean, you know, it's an assertion, it's not explicit in the
verse, but we're saying the word ארור arur in a certain context
if a בית דין beis din is doing it and they're saying
ארור arur be this person, then they're not just calling on God
to curse the person, it's their way of saying we're putting this
person in חרם. cherem. Okay, okay,
בו קללה, bo klala, now, it also means a curse, דכתיב, d'ksiv,
ואלה יעמדו על הקללה, v'eileh ya'amdu al haklala, וכתיב, u'ksiv, ארור האיש
אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה, arur ha'ish asher ya'aseh pesel u'maseicha, right? The
whole curses and blessings on הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל
Har Eival where we used the word ארור. arur. So ארור arur
means cursed be this person. בו שבועה, bo shevuah, it could also
mean a שבועה shvua the same way we just got through saying
that the word אלה ala can mean a שבועה. shvua Okay, בו
שבועה דכתיב, bo shevuah d'ksiv, וישבע יהושע בעת ההיא לאמר ארור האיש
לפני ה'. vayashba Yehoshua ba'eis hahi leimor arur ha'ish lifnei Hashem. So
he he made the people he he imposed an oath on the
people saying cursed be the man. Okay, so you see it's a
good point, again, if you say ארור arur in a certain context,
that's again that whole ambiguity of שבועת האלה. shvuat ha'ala The saying,
like if you think about the case by סוטה, Sotah right? It
says והשביע הכהן את האשה בשבועת האלה. And he says יתן ה'
אותך לאלה ולשבועה בתוך עמך. yitein Hashem osach l'ala v'lishvuah b'soch ameich.
So he never says the word שבועה shvua the כהן, kohein, but
in a certain context like when I say may God curse you
and so on, the idea that that is a שבועה shvua is
somehow implied. All right, so that's again that's that ambiguity. So here
he's saying that ארור arur also in this context by יהושע, Yehoshua,
all the words that יהושע Yehoshua said out of his mouth were
cursed be so and so. But we are saying that in that
context it meant that he he took made he imposed this oath
upon them. So now the גמרא Gemara asks that question the same
way it asked it before by סוטה. Sotah ודילמא תרתי עבד להו?
v'dilma tarti avad lehu? How do you know it means that that
A equals B? Maybe he did both? אשבעינהו ולייטינהו? ashbein'hu v'layitinhu?
He imposed a שבועה shvua and he cursed them, but the word
ארור arur doesn't itself mean a שבועה. shvua אלא מהכא, ella meihacha,
fine, we'll learn it from here. ואיש ישראל נגש ביום ההוא, v'ish
Yisrael nigas bayom hahu,
and that you know and the the and the the people of
Israel that day they were oppressed, ויואל שאול את
העם vayo'el Shaul es ha'am and שאול Shaul imposed an oath on
the people, by the way, notice the verb for the word oath
here is ויואל, vayo'el, which is the word of אלה. ala So
again, the same words for curse are the words for שבועה, shvua
but we're trying to clearly distinguish them or identify them. So anyway,
he imposed an oath on the people לאמר ארור האיש אשר יאכל,
leimor arur ha'ish asher yochal, cursed be the man. Okay, so anyway,
if we just had that verse, we would just say it means
he cursed the people saying cursed be the man who eats anything
today. You might remember that story. And then יהונתן Yehonasan was leading
them into battle and he didn't know about the curse and he
took some of the the honey and so on. Okay, so anyway
the verse says that שאול Shaul cursed the people וכתיב, u'ksiv, and
then a later verse says, ויהונתן לא שמע, v'Yehonasan lo shama, יהונתן
Yehonasan hadn't heard, בהשביע אביו את העם, b'hashbia aviv es ha'am, when
he made them take an oath. So you see the verse is
using the use of the word cursed be so and so as
a type of a sense of an oath. So the גמרא Gemara
says ודילמא הכא נמי תרתי עבד להו? v'dilma hacha nami tarti avad
lehu? Maybe it means both? אשבעינהו ולייטינהו? ashbein'hu v'layitinhu?
Maybe שאול Shaul did both, he made them take an oath and
he cursed them. No, מכתיב וארור? miksiv v'arur? It doesn't say and
cursed, שאול Shaul made them take an oath and he cursed them,
you know, and he said ארור. arur. It says the way he
made them it only did it only says he did one thing.
So therefore you see that saying Saying ארור arur is a way
of imposing an oath. השתא דאתית להכי hashta de'atit lehachi now that
you're saying that, התם נמי לא כתיב וארור hatam nami lo ketiv
ve'arur going back to the case of יהושע, Yehoshua, not just the
case of שאול, Shaul, it also says that יהושע Yehoshua said ארור
arur and then it says that this was an oath. It was
described, it says he imposed an oath on them saying ארור. arur.
So it didn't say he did two things. This is, they're being
identified. So התם נמי לא כתיב
וארור. hatam nami lo ketiv ve'arur.
That's very interesting because
now
what we have
is that
it's very confusing. You have שבועת האלה shvuat ha'ala, which sounds like
are they two things that are being wrapped up in one, but
then what the כהן kohen actually says to her is
יתן השם
אותך לאלה
ולשבועה?
yiten Hashem otach le'ala
velishvua? Is it לשבועה? lishvua? Hold
on. Here,
לאלה ולשבועה בתוך
עמך.
le'ala velishvua betoch
amech.
Now, by the way, that's very interesting. What the heck? Because here's
the problem. If we're identifying these two, which word are we reinterpreting?
Are we reinterpreting the word
ארור arur to mean the word שבועה, shvua. or are we reinterpreting
the word שבועה shvua? to mean the word cursed? If you were
just looking at this verse, the כהן kohen make her took a
שבועת האלה, shvuat ha'ala. may God make you a curse and a
שבועה shvua. בתוך עמך. betoch amech. What does it mean may God
make you a שבועה shvuah בתוך עמך? betoch amech? How does a
person become an
oath? What does that mean? So you could say it means like
people will take an oath, like "I take an oath, let befall
me like befell that woman if I am lying," etc. But certainly
it's a reasonable read of this verse to say that the word
שבועה shvuah sometimes means a curse. Not that the word אלה ala
sometimes means is a שבועה, shvuah but that the word שבועה shvuah,
sometimes means a
curse. That doesn't serve our purposes. We want to maintain these as
very distinct things. A שבועה shvuah. is "I am taking an oath
that I am telling the truth" and an אלה alah is "may
so-and-so befall me." And the way that they are combined is "I
am taking an oath that I am telling the truth and if
I am lying, may so-and-so befall me." You understand those two parts?
שבועה shvuah. is
in the name
of God, basically I am telling the
truth, I am backing up my statement, "In the name of
God, I know no
testimony," the truth. That's the שבועה shvuah part, and the אלה alah.
part is
"and if I'm lying,
let blank befall me." So that's how they're normally combined, the שבועת
האלה. shvuat ha'ala So the point that we're saying is that either
one of them is sufficient. You should be cursed if you know
testimony, or a שבועה shvuah I don't know testimony, either one suffices.
But when you look in the פסוקים, pesukim, they're somehow intertwined and
what does this mean "may God make you a שבועה" shvua etc.
So what the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying by these פסוקים,
psukim, when it says by יהושע, Yehoshua, it says וישבע יהושע vayashba
Yehoshua את העם לאמר
ארור האיש.
et ha'am leimor
arur ha'ish.
That's a little funny because where's the oath
there? It sounds just like he's saying may the person be cursed.
So again, maybe if I was saying the פשט, pshat, maybe what's
implicit is that what he's saying to the people is "I am
implicitly saying that you have to take an oath in God's name
or I'm imposing an oath on you in God's name that you
won't do X, Y, and Z, and if you do X, Y,
and Z then you should be cursed." Somehow that's the שבועה shvua.
part. What's the שבועה shvua. is that somehow an implicit oath that
you won't do the following and so here's the curse. But what
the גמרא Gemara. is reading it is that just by saying may
so-and-so be cursed, if you use the word ארור, arur, you're implicitly
saying, and that's probably a good פשט pshat of the read. If
I say "may you be cursed if blah blah blah," that's being
described as I imposed a שבועה. shvua Why did I impose a
שבועה? shvua. Because it means it's implicitly as if to say "by
God's name I won't do so-and-so and if I do so-and-so, may
this befall me." So that's the idea that the word ארור arur
or the word אלה because that's what you have by שבועת האלה
by עדות edut the פסוק pasuk says ושמעה קול אלה and we
are saying that that means a שבועה. shvua. So all this is
basically saying that sometimes when you say may so-and-so be cursed. Because
you're implicitly saying here's an oath that you're not going to do
it. Okay. And that's somehow that association. So that's you get the
same thing by שאול Shaul and יהונתן, Yehonatan, right, where it says
ויואל שאול, Vayoel Shaul, he made them take an אלה, and he
said ארור האיש. Arur ha'ish. And then it later says by יהונתן,
Yehonatan, it says יהונתן יהונתן
לא שמע.
Yehonatan Yehonatan
lo shamah. What is this? בהשביע behishpia is the פסוק, pasuk, בהשביע
בהשביע אבי.
behishpia behishpia
avi. את העם. at ha'am. I know. Okay, so it's very interesting.
These are really two things, right, one is like an oath that
I'm telling the truth or an oath I won't do this, etc.,
and this is what is going to befall me. Okay. But by
שבועת העדות we only have the cursed part. And what the גמרא
Gemara is doing here is saying when you use the word ארור,
arur, somehow that is, you know, the both
implicitly the שבועה shvua packaged in right together with that.
All right. So let's move on. I hope that was clear. All
right. So now are you laughing because it wasn't? No, it was.
Okay. All right. I mean, because, you know, it's funny, the גמרא
Gemara is trying to disentangle these two. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Yose bar Chanina, says רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Rabbi Yose bar Chanina,
אמן, amen, when somebody says אמן, amen, בו שבועה בו קבלת דברים
בו אמונת דברים. bo shvuah bo kabbalat devarim bo emanut devarim.
Depending on what you're saying אמן amen to, it could either be
accepting a שבועה shvua. on yourself because we learned that before, if
you say אמן amen it's כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי. kemotzi shvuah mipi
dami. Or if you're saying אמן amen to something that a person
is sort of speaking about, accepting an obligation on yourself, when you
say אמן amen then it creates the obligation. Or it's a way
of showing you're affirming something like a claim somebody is making. בו
שבועה, bo shvuah, so it all depends on the context, דכתיב, dichtiv,
ואמרה האשה אמן אמן. ve'amra ha'ishah amen amen.
Okay, the כהן kohen imposes the שבועה shvua. and she says אמן.
amen. בו קבלת דברים, bo kabbalat devarim, דכתיב, dichtiv, ארור אשר לא
יקים את דברי התורה הזאת לעשות אותם, arur asher lo yakim et
divrei hatorah hazot la'asot otam, cursed be the person, ואמר כל העם
אמן. ve'amar kol ha'am amen.
They accept the curse upon themselves if they're lying. בו אמונת דברים,
bo emanut devarim, דכתיב, dichtiv, ויאמר ירמיהו הנביא אמן כן יעשה השם,
vayomer Yirmiyahu hanavi amen ken ya'aseh Hashem,
so should God do, יקים
השם את דבריך, yakim Hashem et devarecha, like when we say אמן
amen to a ברכה, bracha, we're affirming that we believe in it,
believe in the sentiment that was expressed. So it's either like you're
accepting something upon yourself, a שבועה, shvua, an obligation, or you're just
assenting to an idea that was expressed. אמר רבי אליעזר. Amar Rabbi
Eliezer. Anyway the context matters, so the same way the גמרא Gemara
said before the word ארור arur what it means depends on context,
also what אמן amen means depends on context. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar
Rabbi Eliezer,
לאו lav שבועה. shvua, If you just say no I won't do
something, that is an oath. הן hen שבועה. shvua If you say
yes I will do something, that's an oath. That's pretty bizarre. Let's
take a look. בשלמא לאו שבועה דכתיב, Bishlama lav shvuah dichtiv, ולא
יהיה עוד המים למבול. velo yihyeh od hamayim lemabul.
God says I will no longer bring the water for a flood.
וכתיב, Vichtiv, כי מי נח זאת לי, ki mei Noach zot li,
these are the waters of נח, Noach, אשר נשבעתי, asher nishbati, that
I have taken an oath right that I will no longer bring
them. But when did God take an oath? All God says is
I won't do it. So just saying I won't do it is
an oath. Really? Okay, let's finish this and then we'll talk about
it. אלא הן שבועה מנלן? Ela hen shvuah minnalan? Where do we
know that saying yes I will do something is an oath? סברא
הוא. Sevara hu. No, that stands to reason. מדלאו שבועה הן נמי
שבועה, Midelav shvuah hen nami shvuah, from the fact that I won't
do something is an oath, yes I will do something is an
oath. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, והוא דאמר לאו לאו תרי זימני. vehudamar
lav lav trei zimnei. No, no, you can't say every time I
say no I won't it's like a promise or it's an oath,
right? You know, really, there's got to be some line distinguishing. So
you have to double it. No, no, I won't do it. Yes,
yes, I will do it. Okay. והוא דאמר הן הן תרי זימני,
vehudamar hen hen trei zimnei,
because you see that by the case of נח. Noach. ולא יכרת
כל בשר עוד ממי המבול. Velo yikaret kol basar od mimei hamabul.
The waters will not, right, it says I won't do it twice.
There won't be a water for a flood and I won't destroy
all the flesh. ולא יהיה עוד
מים למבול. Velo yihyeh od mayim lemabul. ומדלאו תרי זימני הן נמי
תרי זימני, Umidelav trei zimnei hen nami trei zimnei,
you have to say yes twice. Because obviously what רבא Rava is
doing is he's saying come on, give me a break, you can't
say every time you say you're going to do something it's an
oath. Okay, now how much do we really mean this? That just
saying yes yes, no no, it's an oath. So take a look
at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says והוא דאמר לאו לאו. vehudamar lav
lav. תוספות Tosafot says ולאו דשבועה ממש היא אלא יש להיזהר וקצת
יש עונש בדבר. velav deshvuah mamash hi ela yesh lehizaher vektsat yesh
onesh badavar.
Yeah, it means like, you know, it's a little bit of a
promise essentially. קצת יש להיזהר קצת יש עונש בדבר. ktsat yesh lehizaher
ktsat yesh onesh badavar. You should be careful when you say yes
yes I'll do something, it's like a mini oath, it's like what
you would call a promise. Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says.
He totally downplays the גמרא. Gemara רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד Ra'avad take
the גמרא Gemara seriously. First of all, רמב"ם Rambam says that הן
hen depends, there's a way in which הן hen really is a
שבועה shvua if it's like אמן. amen. If you say to somebody
I say a שבועה shvua upon you that you come and testify
to me if you know עדות edut and you say הן, hen,
yes, it's like saying אמן. amen. Okay, so that's when the word
שבועה shvua is explicitly referenced and you say yes, that's like saying
אמן Amen and that clearly is a שבועה. shvuah, But even if
it's not explicitly referenced, רמב"ם Rambam now remember, רמב"ם Rambam always needs
God's name for it to be a שבועה. shvua So for רמב"ם,
Rambam, what that and you could sort of say you learn it
somewhat from נח Noach because נח Noach has God speaking. So if
even if I say yes, yes, or no, no, I would have
to reference God. So רמב"ם Rambam says it actually is a שבועה
shvua. if I reference God. If I say, yes, yes, in God's
name, I will mow your lawn tomorrow, no, no, in God's name,
as God is my witness, this didn't happen, so that actually is
a שבועה. shvua. Okay, but that makes sense now because you invoked
God's name, now we understand that it's more than just a promise
or statement, you really are sort of taking a שבועה. So רמב"ם
Rambam makes the גמרא Gemara make sense by bringing in God's name
or by saying הין hein was a accepting of a שבועה that
somebody imposed on you, whereas תוספות Tosfot just says the גמרא Gemara
isn't really being serious. It's just sort of using it rhetorically. Do
you need to double it if you're saying in God's name then?
For the רמב"ם Rambam yes, because if I just said to you
in God's name I will do X, Y, and Z, that's not
a שבועה. You need two parts to a שבועה. You need a
technical term that refers to a שבועה, שבועה, מבטא mivta etcetera, and
for רמב"ם, Rambam, ראב"ד Ra'avad you don't always need God's name, but
for רמב"ם Rambam you also need God's name. Those are the two
components. So הין הין hein hein is the technical term for a
שבועה plus God's name. Alright, okay, but if you just say, if
somebody says a שבועה on you and you say הין, hein, one
yes is enough if somebody explicitly imposed a שבועה on you. Alright,
so now the גמרא Gemara, continues. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. איש איש
כי יקלל אלהיו וחיב. Ish ish ki yekalel elohav vechayav. דברי רבי
מאיר. Divrei Rabi Meir. וחכמים פוטרים. Vachachamim potrim.
So now the question is, do you if you use a כינוי
for cursing God or for cursing a parent, are you חייב chayav,
or not? חייב מיתה, chayav misa, the death penalty. So רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir says yes, but the rabbis say no, no, no, you
need שם הוי"ה. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. איש איש כי יקלל אלהיו
ונשא חטאו. Ish ish ki yekalel elohav venasa cheto. מה תלמוד
לומר? Talmud lomar ולאו כבר נאמר Velav kvar ne'emar ונוקב שם ה'
מות יומת? Venoikev shem Hashem mos yumas? If somebody who invokes the
name of God, curses God will be put to death. יכול לא
יהא חייב אלא שם המיוחד בלבד. Yachol lo yehei chayav ela shem
hameyuchad bilvad. Maybe only if you use God's the שם הוי"ה is
a person put to death for cursing God? מנין לרבות את הכינויים?
Minayin lerabos es hakinuyim? How do you know to include any of
the other names of God? תלמוד לומר איש איש כי יקלל אלהיו,
ish ish ki yekalel elohav, because it says again if any man
curses God and it doesn't say the word שם, the name of
God. So that's where רבי מאיר Rabi Meir learns that if you
curse God even without God's explicit name, you're put to death. מכל
מקום. Mikol makom. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim
omrim, and the sages say, על שם המיוחד במיתה ועל הכינויים באזהרה.
Al shem hameyuchad bemisa ve'al hakinuyim be'azhara. No,
no, no. If it's ונוקב שם ה', venoikev shem Hashem, when you
explicate God's name, that's when it's the death penalty. This other verse
that you quote which doesn't say explicate, it just says איש איש
כי יקלל אלהיו, ish ish ki yekalel elohav, yes, we agree it's
prohibited, you do a violation, you transgress the negative prohibition, but it's
not the death penalty. The death penalty requires ונוקב שם ה', venoikev
shem Hashem, God's explicit name. Okay. והמקלל אביו ואמו. Vehamikalel aviv ve'imo.
מאן חכמים? Man chachamim? So now also the same debate about cursing
parents. Does it require God's explicit name to be deserving of the
death penalty? So רבי מנחם בר יוסי, Rabi Menachem bar Yosi, it's
רבי מנחם בר יוסי Rabi Menachem bar Yosi דתניא בברייתא. de-tanya be-braisa.
רבי מנחם בר יוסי אומר, Rabi Menachem bar Yosi oimer, בנוקבו שם
יומת. Benoikvo shem yumas.
So this is again by cursing God and the verse repeats and
says by in his explicating of the name he'll be put to
death. מה תלמוד לומר שם? Ma talmud lomar shem? Why did it
have to say again explicating the name? We said that before. So
why is it repeating it? So לימד על המקלל אביו ואמו Limed
al hamikalel aviv ve'imo that you're not just by cursing God, but
even the other case where cursing gets put to death, cursing a
parent, שאינו חייב עד שיקלל בשם. She'eino chayav ad sheyekalel bashem. So
it's a redundant by cursing God that it mentions the emphasis of
God's name to tell me the other place where there's a death
penalty for cursing, cursing a parent, also requires God's explicit name. רבי
מאיר Rabi Meir disagrees. והמקלל עצמו וחברו. Vehamikalel atzmo vechavero.
Now somebody who curses not a parent or God, but another person
or even curses himself, okay, that you would transgress even without using
God's name. Now what do you transgress? אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rabi
Yannai, ודברי הכל, Vedivrei hakol,
everybody would agree this, meaning even if by parents you need God's
name, that's because it's a death penalty. When it comes to the
prohibition against cursing somebody else, everybody agrees you violate that, you violate
like we sort of said by God as well. You violate the
transgression even without God's explicit name, even with some other name of
God. Now דכתיב, Dechsiv, how do you know about עצמו, atzmo, how
do you know you're not supposed to curse yourself? דכתיב רק השמר
לך ושמור נפשך מאד. Dechsiv rak hishamer lecha ushmor nafshecha me'od.
Guard yourself and protect yourself. So when you curse yourself, it's interesting,
there's a whole discussion like can you risky behavior or can you
smoke, can you do these types of things? Are you violating the
verse that says protect yourself greatly? And that's read to mean like
protect your own health, your own
well-being. The פשט pshat of the verse is not that. The פשט
pshat of the verse is: be very sure you remember the fact
that you stood at הר סיני. Har Sinai. But it's being read
as: protect your own self, you know, take care of yourself. Okay,
so on the one hand that's an interesting question like there's debates,
you know, like רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein writes a whole
תשובה tshuva if you haven't started smoking it's forbidden to begin because
of this מצווה mitzvah of ושמרתם מאד לנפשותיכם, ushmartem me'od lenafshoteichem, right,
והשמר שמור נפשך מאד, v'hishamer shemor nafshecha me'od, protecting your health, protecting
yourself. But the גמרא Gemara here says the idea of protecting yourself
also prohibits you from cursing yourself, which is fascinating, right, which sort
of reflects the idea that they believed in the real efficacy of
the curse. If you curse yourself, you're actually endangering yourself. Okay.
What if somebody already started smoking?
Yeah, so then the רב משה Rav Moshe tries to sort of
explain, you know, you can't tell people to stop if they're already
hooked, whatever, some other discussion. Okay. כדרבי אבין אמר רבי אילא k'd'rabbi
Avin amar Rabbi Ila דאמר כל מקום שנאמר השמר פן ואל אינו
אלא לא תעשה. d'amar kol makom shene'emar hishamer pen ve'al eino ela
lo ta'aseh. If it says guard yourself it means that it's negative,
there's a negative prohibition against endangering yourself. ולחבירו? v'lachaveiro?
How do you know you're not allowed to curse your friend? דכתיב
לא תקלל חרש d'chtiv lo tekalel cheresh don't curse even a deaf
person and חז"ל Chazal understand it means not only a deaf person
but anybody you can't curse. Okay. And therefore but those are prohibited
since they're not the death penalty by any reference to God's name.
All right. So now it says יככה השם אלוקים וכן יככה אלוקים
זו היא אלה הכתובה בתורה. Yakcha Hashem Elokeim vechen yakcha Elokeim zu
hi ala haktuva batorah. So again for שבועת העדות you don't need
a שבועה even an אלה and that's what we that's what we
were talking about about a disentangling the two. And even if you
say may God curse you, you know, יככה השם בשחין ובחדפא Yakcha
Hashem bashichin u'vachadafa or whatever as you quote from the קללות klalot
in the תורה, Torah right, that is an אלה for the purpose
of שבועת העדות. So יתיב רב כהנא קמיה דרב יהודה. Yasiv Rav
Kahana kamei d'Rav Yehuda. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana was sitting in
front of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. יתיב וקאמר Yasiv veka'amar and sitting
and saying, המניסתן כדתנן, Hamasnisin k'detnan,
okay, this משנה, Mishna. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was saying, this משנה,
Mishna, our משנה, Mishna when he was reading the משנה Mishna, he
says, oh if it says יככה השם Yakcha Hashem that would constitute
an אלה for the purposes of שבועת העדות. Okay. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to him, כני, Kanei, no,
you should say it as a euphemism. Don't explicitly read the verse
and say, you know, if I said God should curse you, like
you know we don't do that. We don't say things that we
don't like, we don't want to happen. So you should say God
should curse him. Don't say God should curse you. It's like you're
sort of wishing that upon the people that are in front of
you. Okay, so you should euphemize. I don't know if that's a
verb, but we're going to I'm going to make it a verb.
You should euphemize. יתיב ההוא מרבנן קמיה דרב כהנא. Yasiv hahu mera'banan
kamei d'Rav Kahana.
Now רב כהנא Rav Kahana himself who critiqued רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
he himself you know slipped up as well because he was sitting
so another case a rabbi was sitting in front of רב כהנא
Rav Kahana יתיב וקאמר yasiv veka'amar and oh maybe it says the
rabbi was saying not רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. Maybe רב כהנא Rav
Kahana was playing the same role in both places. Yeah, it makes
actually sense that the rabbi here was saying. How do they translate
that in the English? רב כהנא Rav Kahana was saying?
Wait, a rabbinical student was sitting before רב כהנא Rav Kahana and
he sat and quoted this verse.
Yeah so presumably the student. So both cases רב כהנא Rav Kahana
is playing the same role. Okay. So the student was saying גם
אל יתצך לנצח Gam El yitatzcha lanetzach God should destroy you forever,
יחתך ויסחך מאוהל yichtecha veyisacha me'ohel he should like cut you down
and uproot you from the tent ושרשך מארץ חיים סלה v'shershacha me'eretz
chayim sela and uproot you from the land of of the living.
So it's a pretty heavy verse. Anyway, but it said you. Okay.
And he was saying this verse, hey what about this verse that
says God should curse you? He said excuse me? So אמר ליה
כני. amar lei kanei. You know what? You should say you know
euphemize that, say God should curse him. Don't say don't say it
in the second person. תרתי למה לי Tarti lama li why do
I need both stories? מהו דתימא הני מילי מתניתין Ma'u d'teima hani
mili matnisin maybe you should rephrase the משנה, Mishna. okay that's just
a rabbinic teaching. אבל בקרא אימא לא מכנינן Aval bekra eima lo
machninan if you're quoting a verse that's God's words maybe you have
to quote them directly. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan not that way and
again it doesn't mean like when you're doing a reading the תורה
Torah in the you know reading from the תורה you rephrase things
although there are one or two places in the קללות klalot that
we read a word differently than it's than it's than it's written.
But anyway but if you're referencing it you know you need to
create a little bit of a distance. You shouldn't be implying that
you're you're invoking that verse on the people in front of you.
Even though you're clearly not, you need to say it in a
way that makes clear that that's not what you're saying. Okay. אל
יככה ויברכך. Al yakcha v'yivarechecha.
God should not curse you, he should not smite you if you
are if you come and testify what you know. God should bless
you and give you good things if you come and testify. So
is that a case of a of a of a שבועת העדות?
I don't say God should curse you if you're not coming to
testify. I say if you do come and testify what you know
God should bless you. So does and you say yes fine I
accept that. Okay. So is that now a שבועת העדות? Because I
never said that if you're not going to come God should curse
you. I only said if you do come God should bless you.
Okay? So רבי מאיר מחייב וחכמים פוטרים. Rabbi Meir mechayev vechachamim potrim.
Rabbi Meir says that constitutes a אלה and the חכמים Chachamim say
it does not and you would not be obligated in a קרבן.
korban. So now what is the debate here? The debate is the
classic debate in the גמרא Gemara, whether you say מכלל לאו אתה
שומע הן ומכלל הן אתה שומע לאו. mikh'lal lav atah shome'a hen
umikh'lal hen atah shome'a lav. If somebody says,
if you say X can you infer the not X situation? Now
by the way, as a matter of prepositional logic, you cannot infer.
If I say God should bless you if you come and testify
for me, then that does not mean that if you don't testify
God will curse you, right? It means that if you don't testify
God won't bless you. Actually, no, it actually doesn't even mean that.
It means that if you do testify God will bless you, and
if you don't testify, maybe God will bless you, maybe God won't
bless
you. So that's the way prepositional logic works. Did anybody ever take
prepositional logic in school? Okay, let's see. If you say if P
then Q, that does not imply if not P then not Q.
If you testify God will bless you, if you don't testify God
will curse you, that's not what it implies. What it implies is
if not Q then not P. Okay? If you testify God will
bless you would mean that if you are not blessed, clearly you
did not come and testify. I don't know if I just confused
everybody once again. Anyway, the point is just because I say God
will bless you if you come testify does not mean that God
will curse you if you don't testify. Technically it doesn't mean that,
but in the way that people talk, it does mean that. All
right? So that is the question: should we say that הלכתית, halachit,
if I say God shouldn't curse you if you come testify, that
what the meaning of that is הלכתית halachit is what people mean
it to mean, which is that God will curse you if you
don't come and testify? So that's the debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says you're חייב, chaiv. the חכמים Chachamim say you're פטור. patur. So
the גמרא Gemara, says הליתא לדרבי מאיר מכלל לאו אתה שומע הן?
haleisa led'Rabbi Meir mikh'lal lav atah shome'a hen? But we know elsewhere
when it comes to making תנאים in stipulations, like where we're making
a contract and I say if you do X, Y, and Z
then you'll get a bonus, and if you don't do it you
won't get a bonus or whatever it will be, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says if you want a stipulation to be binding you can't
just say one side of the stipulation. You have to say if
P then Q and if not P then not Q. You have
to say both sides of the stipulations. Okay? So how come here
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir seems to be taking the position that you
would infer the yes from the no and the no from the
yes if normally he doesn't say that? So the גמרא Gemara says
כי אתא רב יצחק תנא כדתנן, ki ata Rav Yitzchak tana k'detnan,
so איפכא, ipcha, I'm sorry. So he says fine, reverse the positions
in our משנה. Mishna, You're right, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir normally requires
you say it both ways, we'll say the same is true by
this אלה. That the חכמים Chachamim say it's enough to say may
God bless you and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say it's not
enough. כי אתא רב יצחק תנא כדתנן. ki ata Rav Yitzchak tana
k'detnan. Now when רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, he taught a ברייתא which was just like our משנה, Mishna
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said you don't have to say it
both ways, you don't have to say it in the negative. אמר
רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, השתא
דאנן תנן הכי, hashta d'anan tnan hachi, that's the tradition of the
משנה Mishna we have here in בבל, Bavel, וכי אתא רב יצחק
תנא הכי, v'chi ata Rav Yitzchak tana hachi, and when רב יצחק
Rav Yitzchak came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that was also the
tradition he had in the משנה, Mishnah
so שמע מינה דוקא תנן, sh'ma mina davka tnan, we can't go
playing around with the text of the משנה. Mishnah, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir really says that it's enough to say it in the positive.
But how does this fit with the fact that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir normally needs you say it both ways? אלא קשיא, ela kashya,
so it's difficult. What do you how do you resolve it? So
כי לית ליה בממונא אבל באיסורא אית ליה. ki leit leh b'mamona
aval b'issura it leh. When does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say you
have to say it both ways? That's in monetary matters, but not
in issues of transgression. So what does this mean? Presumably
there's two ways of understanding this. One way, which I'd like to
understand it but it doesn't really fit in the גמרא, Gemara is
if I'm making a contract there with Gloria, okay, I have to,
for if
it's not enough to say well obviously if I said if P
then Q I meant if not P then not Q. If Gloria's
going to have to be bound by it, I can't make something
implicit, I have to be explicit, right? And if P then Q
does not mean if not P then not Q, then Gloria can
say I'm not obligated, I'm sorry, that wasn't in the contract. Okay?
So when we're dealing with stipulations about monetary matters between people etc.,
there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you have to say both sides
of it. When we're talking about transgressions, so it's enough to say
one side. Now of course the problem though is that if I
say if you know testimony if you come testify God will bless
you, it's also about another person, right? There are two sides to
this. So why shouldn't that require me to be explicit about the
flip side of it? So it sounds like the other point that's
being made is if it's something weighty like not just a contract
but weighty like a transgression, then we would obviously sort of read
it in the strictest
way. So because it's a weighty issue of calling a curse upon
you, a שבועה, and so on, that's why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
said in that case I'll assume it means the sort of weightier
read of it and I'll assume it means the flip side of
it as well. Okay? So that case רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would
agree. אבל באיסורא. aval b'issura. so the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
הרי סוטה דאיסורא, harei Sotah de'issura, סוטה Sotah. is an issue about
a violation of a שבועה and her acting in ways of violation
ואמר, ve'amar, and one of the verses we had to challenge רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir, who said you need it both ways, was how
can you say you need it both ways? It doesn't say by
a סוטה Sotah, both ways; it says, if you did not sin,
you should be cleansed from this שבועה. So that's very nice, but
it doesn't say if you did sin, you'll be punished. Right? So
that was the case by סוטה; Sotah didn't say the negative. And
nevertheless, so that—and in the גמרא, Gemara not this גמרא, the גמרא
that deals with רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir requirements that stipulations occur in
both directions, we said how come by סוטה Sotah it's not in
both directions if you normally require both directions? Okay. And the answer
was הנקי כתיב. hinaki ksiv. Now what does הנקי כתיב hinaki ksiv
mean? It means הנקי, hinaki, we read it as saying חנקי. khinaki.
So it says
if you didn't sin, you'll be cleansed. So the question was: ah,
רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, why doesn't it say it in the other
direction? And the answer was: it does say it in the other
direction, because you can mean הנקי hinaki as חנקי. khinaki. If you
didn't say it—if you did sin, you should be strangled. Okay, you
should be put to death. So we do a play on words
to say the verse does say it in both directions. So טעמא
דכתיב הנקי. taima dechsiv hinaki. So רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir defense of
סוטה Sotah was, oh it says הנקי, hinaki, so it's like it
means it in both directions. הא לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, if
it was not that, מכלל דהשומע הן לאו אמנין, miklal adhashma hein
lo amnin, he would have had to concede that you don't need
it to be said in both directions. But why was סוטה Sotah?
a problem for רבי מאיר? Rebbe Meir? If רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
agrees that by cases of איסור issur you don't need both directions,
why was סוטה Sotah an issue for him? סוטה is a case
of איסור. issur. So the גמרא says אלא איפכא, ella eipach, fine,
let's go back to our verse again. Okay, we'll go back to
our verse and we'll say that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir in our
משנה, Mishnah רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir actually
does require both directions even in איסור, issur, just like he did
by סוטה. And—and that's why רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says here too
you need both directions. We'll reverse the positions. אפילו באיסורא לית ליה,
afilu be'issura leis lei, even by איסור, issur, רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
says one direction is not enough, you need both directions. And that's
why in our משנה we'll reverse the positions. Okay, so now what
we do is we want everything to be nice and neat. רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir always requires both directions whether it's a stipulation, whether
it's סוטה, whether it's our case of the שבועה. So saying may
God bless you is not enough. We'll have רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
be the one that says that position and the חכמים Chachamim say
it's always enough to say one direction. So the גמרא says מתיקיף
לה רבינא. matkif la Ravina. So רבינא Ravina asked on this: ובאיסורא
לית ליה? Ube'issura leis lei? Does רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir really by
איסור issur
say that you know—not—not think that one direction is sufficient? אלא מעתה
שתוי יין ופרועי ראש במיתה. Ella mei'ata shetuyei yayin upruei rosh bamisah.
How do you know that if somebody is drunk and enters into
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or you know, his hair's grown wild,
he hasn't gotten a haircut in thirty days, and he goes into
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, how do you know that it's liable
to the death penalty? הכי נמי דלית ליה לרבי מאיר? Hachi nami
deleis lei leRebbe Meir? Would רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir say that that's
not true? Because the verse by there only says, you know, do
not be drunk and then you won't die. So the implication is
if you are drunk you will die. But it was only said
in one direction. So if רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir always requires both
directions, would you say that he would not agree that this is
punishable by death? Or death by heaven? דתנן אלו שבמיתה, Detnan eilu
shebemisah, the following are with the death penalty: שתוי יין ופרועי ראש.
shetuyei yayin upruei rosh. So you see even רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
has to agree, right? You get this? That the verse only says
if you are not drunk you won't die. So even רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir agrees sometimes one direction does imply the other. Okay. And
presumably that's because that's a case of איסור. issur. That's a case
of prohibition. So presumably רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir is saying—would concede that
when you're dealing with a case of prohibition
one direction really would suffice. Okay. אלא לעולם תיפוך, Ella le'olam teipach,
fine fine, keep it reversed and כי לית ליה בממונא באיסורא אית
ליה. ki leis lei bemamona, be'issura is lei. Like you just sort
of showed to me that he holds it by—I'm sorry that I'm
a little rushing through this, but here let's try to do this.
I'm sorry, just give me one more minute. Okay here you have
the following cases. Our case of the משנה is the שבועת העדות.
Okay,
you have that. You have the case about normal contracts,
you have the case of סוטה and you have the case of—of
שתוי יין. shetuyei yayin. Okay?
Where the verse only says, you know, don't drink, you know, ולא
תמותו, velo tamusu, that you won't die if you're not drunk, which
implies that if you are—so what's the basic point? Okay. So רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir by contracts he says that you need it to
go in both directions. By סוטה he says you need it go
in both directions. By שתוי יין shetuyei yayin though, everybody agrees that
שתוי יין shetuyei yayin you're חייב. chayav and it only went in
one direction. Okay, so how are we going to reconcile? So we're
going to say fine, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we're going to reverse
it. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in our משנה will also say שבועת
העדות needs to be both directions. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir always
needs everything both directions except this one case. So what's the reason
that this case stands out? This is a case of איסור, issur,
right?
This
is
a case, you know, this is a case of איסור, issur, this
is a case of איסור, issur, right? So if איסור issur he
needs one direction suffices, how come here you need both directions? So
the גמרא says אלא לא תיהפוך ela lo seihapoch דכי לית ליה
בממונא באיסורא אית ליה. d'chi leis lei bamamona be'issura is lei. By
איסור issur one direction suffices. So one minute. So why here do
you need both directions? He says ושאני איסורא דסוטה דאיסורא דאית ליה
ממונא נמי. ushani issura d'Sotah de'issura d'is lei mamona nami. So סוטה
has a ממון mamon component. What's the ממון mamon component of סוטה?
The ממון mamon component of סוטה is that to exempt from paying
the כתובה. Kesubah. And the ממון mamon component of שבועת העדות is
you want somebody to testify in your case of, you know, in
your in your monetary case. Okay, so what we're saying is in
all these cases because there's a monetary component, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
requires both directions. Whereas in this case because it's all just about
the Torah prohibiting, it's enough to say it in one direction. Alright,
so I was a little bit quick, but I hope you got
the idea. So bottom line in our משנה, if you say "May
God bless you", רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say you're exempt because
we're reversing the names in our משנה and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
requires it in both directions. And the חכמים Chachamim would say you're
חייב because the חכמים Chachamim one direction you imply the other direction.
All right, I hope that was clear enough. All right, we'll end
with this for now.